GRADUATE STUDENT · COMPUTATIONAL EVOLUTIONARY BIOLOGIST · SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

Harms Lab · Department of Chemistry & Biochemistry · University of Oregon

# Research Interests\_

I am physicist, turned software developer, turned evolutionary biologist. Having worked in the biological sciences throughout by graduate career, I have been acutely aware that they lag behind in software. I would like to push to field into the modern software world by leveraging and developing tools like Jupyter, XX, and XX.

# Education

PH.D. IN CHEMISTRY AND BIOCHEMISTRY

Sep. 2013 - June 2018

University of Oregon **B.S. IN PHYSICS** 

San Luis Obispo, CA

Eugene, OR

CALIFORNIA POLYTECHNIC STATE UNIVERSITY

Sep. 2009 - Jun. 2013

# **Research Positions**

GRADUATE RESEARCH STUDENT MICHAEL J HARMS, PHD

Eugene, OR

University of Oregon

Sep. 2013 - Preser

CORE DEVELOPER BRIAN GRANGER, PhD

San Luis Obispo, CA

PYTHON-JUPYTER TEAM

Dec. 2012 - Sep. 2013

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH STUDENT JONATHAN FERNLER, PHD

San Luis Obispo, CA

CAL POLY SAN LUIS OBISPO

Jun. 2011 - Jul. 2013

# **Publications**

SAILER ZS\*, HARMS MJ

PNAS

"Molecular ensembles make evolution unpredictable"

2017

SAILER ZS\*, HARMS MJ

PLOS Computational Biology

"High-order epistasis shapes evolutionary trajectories"

Genetics

SAILER ZS\*, HARMS MJ

2017

"Detecting high-order epistasis in nonlinear genotype-phenotype maps"

In Prep

**SAILER ZS\***, HARMS MJ "Epistasis as uncertainty."

2018

SAILER ZS\*, SUMMERS RL, SHAFIK SH, JOULE A, MARTIN RE, AND HARMS MJ

In Prep

 $\hbox{``Predicting evolutionary trajectories towards chloroquine resistance in a plasmodium falciparum}$ 

. . . . .

genotype-phenotype map."

2018

# **Presentations**

Invited Talk · "Resurrecting ancient proteins in Python."

Austin, TX

SciPy

JUPYTERCON

Invited Talk · "How Jupyter makes experimental and computational collaborations easy"

NYC. NY

Invited Talk · "High-order epistasis makes evolution unpredictable"

Aug. 2017
Austin, TX

Society of Molecular Biology and Evolution

, 1030111, 171

**Poster** · "High-order Interactions Create Long-Term Memory in Protein Evolution."

Carbondale, IL

GIBBS SOCIETY FOR BIOTHERMODYNAMICS

Oct. 2016

**Poster** · "Long-term memory in Molecular Evolution Shapes Evolutionary Outcomes."

St. Louis, MO May 2016

Protein Folding Consortium

**Poster** · "High-order Epistasis in Genotype-Phenotype Maps Shapes Evolutionary Outcomes"

11ay 2010

GIBBS SOCIETY FOR BIOTHERMODYNAMICS

Carbondale, IL

PROTEIN FOLDING CONSORTIUM

Invited Talk · "Dielectric Spectroscopy in Liquid Crystals"

AMERICAN PHYSICS SOCIETY, CALFORNIA-NEVADA SECTION

May 2015

San Luis Obispo, CA

# **Highlighted Open-Source Software**

#### **CONTRIBUTOR JUPYTER NOTEBOOKS**

Web application that allows you to create and share documents that contain live code, equations, visualizations and explanatory text.

https://github.com/jupyter/notebook

## **CONTRIBUTOR IPYTHON**

Command shell for interactive computing in Python that offers introspection, rich media, shell syntax, tab completion, and history.

https://github.com/ipython/ipython

## **CONTRIBUTOR** LATTICEPROTEINS

2d lattice protein simulator written in Python.

https://github.com/jbloomlab/latticeproteins

#### **CONTRIBUTOR BIOPYTHON**

Python tools for computational molecular biology.

https://github.com/biopython/biopythor

#### **CONTRIBUTOR** NETWORKX

Python package for complex networks.

https://github.com/networkx/networkx

#### OWNER NX\_ALTAIR

NetworkX graphs in Altair.

https://github.com/zsailer/nx\_altair

#### OWNER PANDAS\_FLAVOR

The easy way to write your own flavor of Pandas.

https://github.com/zsailer/pandas\_flavor

## **OWNER** EPISTASIS

Python API for estimating statistical high-order epistasis in large genotype-phenotype maps.

https://github.com/harmslab/epistasis

## OWNER GPMAP

Python API for analyzing, manipulating, and simulating large genotype-phenotype map data.

https://github.com/harmslab/gpmap

## **OWNER** PHYLOPANDAS

Pandas DataFrames for Phylogenetics

https://github.com/zsailer/phylopandas

## **OWNER** PHYLOVEGA

Declarative tree visualizations in Python powered by Vega

https://github.com/zsailer/phylovega

#### **OWNER PHYLOGENETICS**

Python API for managing phylogenetic projects

https://github.com/zsailer/phylogenetics

#### OWNER PYASR

Ancestral Sequence Reconstruction in Python

https://github.com/zsailer/pyasr

# Honors & Awards

## **SCHOLARSHIP RECIPIENT**

Austin, TX

SCIPY 2017

New York City, NY

TRAVEL AWARD
JUPYTERCON 2017

YTERCON 2017 August 2017

July 17, 2018 Zachary Sailer · CV 2

SCHOLARSHIP RECIPIENT

Austin, TX

SciPy 2017

ART ROSEN MEMORIAL SCHOLAR San Luis Obispo, CA

TOP STUDENT IN QUANTUM LABORATORY

May 2012

**Teaching** 

REPRODUCIBILITY AND OPEN SCIENCE POWERED BY JUPYTER

June 20

Guest lecture introducing bioinformatics graduate students to Jupyter Lab, Binder, and RISE for reproducible research. ( 20 students)

Working on Github as a team September 2017

Guest lecture introducing bioinformatics graduate students how to contribute to open source projects on Github. (20 students)

REPRODUCIBILITY AND OPEN SCIENCE POWERED BY JUPYTER

July 20:

Guest lecture introducing bioinformatics graduate students to the Jupyter Notebook and how it can be used for reproducible research. (20 students)

SCIENTIFIC PYTHON COURSE (TA)

March-June 201

Introduce graduate students to scientific computing, basic machine-learning, and image processing in Python. (20 students)

COLLABORATING ON CODE

July 2016

Guest lecture introducing bioinformatics graduate students to clone, sharing, and collaborating on code using Git and Github (20 students).

GENERAL CHEMISTRY LABORATORY (TA) 2013-2014

Introduce undergraduates to general chemistry laboratory techniques (40 students).

**Mentoring** 

LEANDER GOLDBACH INTERNATIONAL MASTERS STUDENT

May 2018 - August 2018

adas

**DOUG SCHUETT** SUMMER PROGRAM FOR UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH (SPUR) STUDENT

Summer 2018

adas

THOMAS BAILEY BIOCHEMISTRY GRADUATE STUDENT

Winter 2017

adas

ABRAHAM RICKETT BIOCHEMISTRY UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT

Winter 2015 - Spring 2017

adas

SOFIE CHRISTIE ACADEMY FOR SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING HIGH SCHOOL INTERN

Summer 201

adas